Inventory of the Ferdinand Peroutka papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Ferdinand Peroutka papers
1935-1978
84052
Hoover Institution Archives
16 manuscript boxes, 41 sound tape reels (10.8 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, writings, and printed matter, relating to postwar conditions in Czechoslovakia, the internal administration of Radio Free Europe, and Czechoslovak émigré politics.
Peroutka, Ferdinand
Access
Collection is open for research.
Use copies of all sound recordings in this collection are available for immediate access.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1984.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Ladislav Feierabend papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Michal Múdry papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Radio Free Europe broadcast records, Hoover Institution Archives
Radio Free Europe corporate records, Hoover Institution Archives
Jaroslav Stránský papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Josef Škvorecký papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
1895 February 6 Born, Prague, Austro-Hungary
1919-1923 Editor, the daily Tribuna
1924-1939 Co-founder and Editor-in-Chief, the weekly Přítomnost (founded with support from President Tomáš Garrigue Masaryk, and with Karel Čapek and other prominent writers as regular contributors) Editor, the daily Lidové noviny
1925 Author, Boje o dnešek
1933-1938 Author, Budování státu, a multiple-volume monograph
1939-1945 Imprisoned, Dachau and Buchenwald concentration camps
1945-1946 Member, Czechoslovak National Assembly
1945-1948 Editor, the daily Svobodné noviny
1946-1948 Editor-in-Chief, the weekly Dnešek
1947 Author, Tak nebo tak
1948 Author, Oblak a valčík: kolektivní drama o dvanácti obrazech Immigrated to London, Great Britain; published in émigré periodicals throughout his career (Hlas domova, Americké listy, České slovo, and others)
1949 Author, Byl Edvard Beneš vinen?
1950 Moved to New York, USA
Circa 1950-1957 Member, Rada svobodného Československa (The Council of Free Czechoslovakia)
1950-1964 Editor-in-Chief, Radio Free Europe Czechoslovak Desk
1951-1977 Author, weekly broadcast addresses in Radio Free Europe (published as a three-volume monograph Mluví k vám Ferdinand Peroutka: rozhlasové komentáře rádia Svobodná Evropa, 2003-2006)
1955 Married Slávka Fenclová
1959 Author, Democratic Manifesto
1976 Author, Oblak a valčík: román
1978 April 20 Died, New York
Scope and Content of Collection
Contains correspondence with prominent Czechoslovak cultural and political figures in Czechoslovakia and in exile, and with American intellectual elites, as well as Peroutka's writings in exile. Also included are correspondence and internal documents of Radio Free Europe and the Council of Free Czechoslovakia (Rada svobodného Československa). Transcripts of Peroutka's radio addresses and sound recordings of Radio Free Europe programs form the final and most extensive part of the collection.
Radio Free Europe.; Czechoslovakia--Emigration and immigration.; Radio broadcasting--Europe, Eastern.; Czechoslovakia--History--1945-1992.; Journalists.; Audiotapes.
- Correspondence, 1935-1978, undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains correspondence with prominent Czechoslovak cultural and political figures in Czechoslovakia and in exile, with American intellectual elites, letters related to Radio Free Europe and to Peroutka's writings, as well as other correspondence. Arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
  - Altschul, Frank, 1951-1957 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Includes a report on the public image of Edvard Beneš in post-war Czechoslovakia
  - Andrial, J., 1951 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Bachstein, Martin Karl, 1970 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Bechyně, Zdeněk, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Belák, [?], 1960 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Bělehrádek, Jan, 1952 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Beneš, Jan, 1975 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Beneš, Vojta, 1950, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Bernard, Vilém, 1955, 1965 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Bosl, Karl, 1975 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Bryan, David Tennant, 1959 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Bubák, Vladimír, 1975 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Buber-Neumann, Margarete, 1954 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Contains a letter with questions on Milena Jesenská
  - Ciprisová, Hana, 1974, 1976 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Československý poradní sbor v západní Evropě (Czechoslovak Advisory Committee in Western Europe), 1978 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Československý zahraniční ústav v exilu, 1956 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Contains a report on Peroutka's view of the Sudeten-German question
  - Čížek, Alojz, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - dos Passos, John, 1959 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Dostál, A., 1972 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Drábek, Jan, 1977 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Drábek, Jaroslav, 1977 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Dresler, Jaroslav, 1959, 1976, 1978 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Eliáš, Zdeněk, 1961 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Feierabend, Ladislav, 1953 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Feldstein, Petr, Student: Týdeník československého svazu mládeže, 1968 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Firt, Julius, 1951-1977, undated (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Fuka, Vladimír, 1975 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Galantière, Lewis, 1956, 1959 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Griffith, William E., 1951 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Hájek, H.J., Skutečnost: Independent Review in Czech and Slovak, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Havel, Václav, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Heidler, Alexander, 1954, 1959 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Heidrich, Arnošt, 1953-1968, undated (Box-folder 1: 5)
    Includes his personal recollections of World War II, including his imprisonment by the Gestapo, and a letter from his family on his passing
  - Herben, Ivan, 1953 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Herget, Anton, 1973 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Hladík, J., Československá obec legionářská v exilu - Francie, 1957 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Hlavatý, V., 1950 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Holešovský, V., 1956 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Holman, Josef A., 1976, undated (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Hostaša, Zdeněk, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Hostovský, Egon, 1957, 1961 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    Contains a report on behalf of Hostovský to John Richardson, Jr.
  - Hrabík, Martin, 1976 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Hrubý, Jiří, 1971 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Ingr, [?], 1971 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    Contains a report on a meeting with Erich von Manstein
  - Jackson, C.D., 1953, 1959 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Jelínek, Ivan, 1950 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Jelínek, Yeshayahu, 1973 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Jelinowiczová?, Jiřina, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Jezdinský, Karel, 1973 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Jiráková, Blanka, 1973 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Jiránek, Milo, 1978 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Jiránek, Miloš, 1978 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Jonáš, Josef, 1956 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Káča (Kateřina), United Nations, 1974 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Kadavý, Ladislav, 1968 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Karsten, Jan, 1954 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Klátil, [?], 1959 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Klofáč, V., 1935 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Kodíček, Milan, 1952 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Kohák, Miloslav, 1952, 1954 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Kolár, Jan M., 1954-1957 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Kolowrat, Jindřich, 1972? (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Kopf, Max, 1953 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Kostrba-Skalický, O., 1953 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Kovárnová, Jarmila, 1952 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Koželuhová-Procházková, Helena, 1951, 1954 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Krizova, Marie, 1974 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Krno, Ladislav G., 1956 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Kulhánek, Vladimír, 1961 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Lamač, Karel, 1951 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Laušman, [?], 1950 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Lederer, Jiří, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Lederer, Zdeněk, undated (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Lehrman, Hal, 1950 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Liehm, A.J., 1974 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Lorenc, Jan, 1951 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Lukas, Jan, 1968 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Luža, Radomír, 1952 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - M., M., 1968 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    Contains a letter on the situation in Czechoslovakia after the Prague Spring events, and a photograph of the National Museum in Prague
  - Mabey, Melvin P., 1954 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Macek, Josef, 1967 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Machatka, Otakar, 1953 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Machatý, Gustav, 1955 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Majer, Václav, 1955 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Mandlová, Adina, 1965, 1978, undated (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Marie, London, 1954 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Masaryková, [?], 1953 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Matějka, Ladislav, 1952-1957 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Matissek, Theo P., 1952 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Matzker, Karl, 1954 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Milčic, Richard, undated (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Mládek, Jan, 1973, 1978 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Múdry, Michal, 1972 (Box-folder 1: 10)
    Also contains letters by Jaroslav Pecháček
  - Nábělek, Jan, 1952 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Němec, František, 1954 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Němeček, Zdeněk, 1950-1957 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Neuwirth, Hans, 1961 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Oberland, O.K., 1956 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Pachman, Luděk, 1972-1977 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    Contains a report on a conversation with Pachman, then a recent émigré, on general conditions in Czechoslovakia and on the regime's treatment of anti-government politicians after the Prague Spring
  - Parrott, Cecil, 1978 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Pecháček, Jaroslav, 1973 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Pejskar, Josef, 1956, 1959, undated (Box-folder 1: 11)
    Contains a letter signed by Petr Z. [Zenkl?]
  - Pelikán, Jiří, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Pitter, Přemysl, 1965, 1975 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Procházka, Adolf, 1965 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Přístupa, Gustav, 1953 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    Also contains letters to Petr Zenkl
  - Rádl, Ota and Lucie Rádlová, 1951 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Ramičová, Alena, 1973 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Rašín, M., 1951 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Růžičková, Svatava, 1954, 1956 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Schoenbaum, Emil, 1951 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Schultz, Milan, 1974 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Sedlák, Mirko, 1956 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Seton-Watson, 1958 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Slabey, Andrew P., 1972 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Sokol - Tělocvičná jednota v Paříži, 1958 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Sokolová, Meda, 1951-1956, undated (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Součková, Milada, 1957, 1972 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Sousedík, [?], 1972 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Společnost pro vědy a umění (Czechoslovak Society of Arts and Sciences in America), 1977 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Steinbach, Karel, 1971 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Stránský, Jan, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 1: 13)
    Includes a letter from Slávka Peroutková to Míla and Eva, and a letter from Míla
  - Stránský, Jaroslav, 1950-1964, undated (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Svoboda, Vladimír, Naarden Movement, 1970 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Šejbalová, Jiřina, 1956 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Škvor, Jiří and Pavel Javor, 1956, 1957 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Škvorecký, Josef and Zdena (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Škvorecká, 1973-1978, undated (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Štěpán, B., 1974 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Švehla, Antonín, 1975 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Švehlová-Černá, Helena, 1958 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Thompson, Dorothy, 1958 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Tigrid, Pavel, 1956, 1977 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Toyen, 1956-1958 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Urzidil, Johannes, 1959 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Valenta, Jaromír, 1950 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Válgiová?, Líza, 1954 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Váňa, František, 1969-1973 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Vedeler, Harold C., 1950 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Vilím, Blažej, 1968 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Vořtenský [?], Józa, 1961 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Voskovec, Jiří, 1950-1965, undated (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Vrázová, Vlasta, 1950, 1956 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Walter, Josef, 1977 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Werich, Jan, 1975, 1977 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - Zedwitz, J., 1952 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Zeman, Karel, 1968 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Zenkl, Petr, 1955-1960 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Zich, Jaroslav V., ú střední svaz československého studentstva v exilu, 1954 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Žáčková-Batková, Jaromíra, 1952 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Official letters from Moscow by Klement Gottwald and Zdeněk Fierlinger, typescripts, 1943 December 21 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - Unidentified correspondence, 1971, 1976, undated (Box-folder 1: 23)
- Writings, 1946-1978, undated
  Contains writings by or about Peroutka, including typescripts of his essays, plays, and other writings, reviews of his writings and related documents, newspaper clippings including caricatures of him in the Czechoslovak domestic press, interviews, and materials related to his passing in 1978. Arranged by subject.
  - Writings and interviews in typescript, 1946-1970, undated (Box-folder 1: 24)
  - Rozhovor mezi p. Simonem, představitelem dra. Lodgmana, a p. Peroutkou and Interview of Mr. Simon, Representative of Dr. Lodgman, with Mr. Peroutka, 1953 April 20 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    Contains a handwritten record of the conversation on the Sudeten-German question and an English translation in typescript
  - Cartoons on or caricatures of Peroutka and Radio Free Europe in the Soviet bloc press, 1953 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Reviews, comments, newspaper clippings and related materials on Peroutka's book Democratic Manifesto, 1959-1963, undated (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Byl Beneš vinen?, pamphlet, and its translation Was Eduard Beneš guilty?, typescript, 1973, undated (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Obituaries, telegrams, newspaper clippings and related materials on Peroutka's passing, 1978 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - If I Were Born Again, typescript of a play, undated (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Šťastlivec Sulla, typescript of a play, undated (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Reviews of Peroutka's books, by Jaroslav Dresler and by an unknown author, undated (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Boje o dnešek, photocopy of Peroutka's book published in 1925 (Box-folder 2: 9-10)
  - Tak nebo tak, photocopy of Peroutka's book published in 1947 (Box-folder 2: 11)
- Newspaper Clippings and Reports, circa 1951-1978
  Contains articles by or about Peroutka and about Czechoslovak affairs in American émigré and Czechoslovak domestic press. Arranged generally in the original order.
  - Newspapers clippings and reports, circa 1951-1978 (Box-folder 3: 1-3)
  - Newspapers clippings, circa 1960s (Box-folder 3: 4)
- Rada svobodného Československa (The Council of Free Czechoslovakia) Documents, 1950-1957, undated
  Contains correspondence, reports and other materials, also related to the Radio Free Europe.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1950-1953 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - 1954 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - 1955 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - 1956-1957 and undated (Box-folder 4: 1)
- Radio Free Europe Internal Documents, 1950-1977, undated
  Contains reports, correspondence and related documents on current political events in Czechoslovakia, on the affairs within the Czechoslovak desk, and on Peroutka's writings.
  Arranged chronologically in two groups.
  - Radio Free Europe documents, 1950-1954 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Radio Free Europe documents, 1955 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Radio Free Europe documents, circa 1950s (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Radio Free Europe documents, 1960-1977 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Radio Free Europe documents, undated (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - RFE Kostrba Affair, a folder with correspondence and reports on tensions within the RFE Czechoslovak Desk, 1960-1961, undated (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - The Czecho-Slovak Problem: Answer to the Memorandum of Mr. Matus Cernak entitled "The Slovaks and Radio Free Europe,", undated (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - The Czechoslovak Problem and the Radio Free Europe: Reply to the Memorandum Submitted by the Slovak Liberation Committee, undated (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Have Czech and Slovak Exiles Collaborated with Communism?: Second Part of the Answer to the Memorandum of the Slovak Liberation Committee, undated (Box-folder 4: 10)
- Radio Free Europe Broadcast Transcripts, 1951-1976
  Contains transcripts of Peroutka's weekly addresses, the so-called Sunday Talks or Weekly Talks, and their English translations, in typescript. Arranged chronologically.
  - Odpověd Mr. C. D. Jacksonovi and its translation, Peroutka's speech: Special broadcast, 1951 May 1 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - 1951 May - 1954 April (Box-folder 5: 2-13)
  - 1954 May - 1955 September (Box-folder 6: 1-11)
  - 1955 October - 1956 August (Box-folder 7: 1-10)
  - 1956 September - 1957 July (Box-folder 8: 1-10)
  - 1957 August - 1958 June (Box-folder 9: 1-10)
  - 1958 July - 1959 October (Box-folder 10: 1-11)
  - 1959 November - 1961 December (Box-folder 11: 1-9)
  - 1962 January - 1963 August (Box-folder 12: 1-8)
  - 1963 September - 1965 May (Box-folder 13: 1-10)
  - 1965 June - 1968 April (Box-folder 14: 1-12)
  - 1968 May - 1972 February (Box-folder 15: 1-14)
  - 1972 March - 1976 December (Box-folder 16: 1-11)
- Radio Free Europe Broadcast Sound Recordings, 1955-1956, undated
  Contains Peroutka's play Šťastlivec Sulla, his weekly addresses, and other Radio Free Europe programs; 41 reels, transferred to digital files in June 2010. Arranged generally in the original order.
  - Ferdinand Peroutka: Šťastlivec Sulla, Part 1, in Czech, undated (Reel 1)
    Access
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003643 (part)
    Contains an introductory commentary and the first part of a Radio Free Europe production of the play
  - Ferdinand Peroutka: Šťastlivec Sulla, Part 2, in Czech, undated (Reel 2)
    Contains the second part of a Radio Free Europe production of the play.
  - Ferdinand Peroutka: Šťastlivec Sulla, Part 3, in Czech, undated (Reel 3)
    Contains the third part of a Radio Free Europe production of the play.
  - Radio Free Europe recording and report of Zdeněk Němeček's funeral services in Munich and New York, with speeches read by Julius Firt, Jan Tumlíř, Ferdinand Peroutka, Egon Hostovský, Jaroslav Drábek and Karel Steinbach, and with a reading from Němeček's writings, in Czech, undated (Reel 4)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003646
  - Fragment of an interview with Peroutka by Kárnet (?), in Czech, undated (Reel 5)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003647
    On the beginnings of his career as a writer, on the foundation of Czechoslovakia in 1918, and on other political issues
  - Fragment of an interview with Peroutka by Kárnet (?), in Czech, undated (Reel 6)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003649
    On the beginnings of his journalistic career, on the Rozvoj periodical, and on Russian literature and political culture
  - A weekly commentary of Ferdinand Peroutka, in Czech, 1955 April 30 (Reel 7)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003651
    On the image of women in Soviet discourse
  - Rozhlasový lekár radio program, in Slovak, 1956 November 10 (Reel 8)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003652 (part)
    Dr. Jozef Jakši and moderator Peter Račkovský discuss health issues
  - A weekly commentary of Ferdinand Peroutka, in Czech, 1956 November 10 (Reel 8)
    On the 1956 Hungarian Revolution
  - Sokolská hlídka radio program, in Czech, March 17 (Reel 9)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003653 (part)
    Commentaries by Marie Provazníková, Antonín Hřebík, Jarmila Uhlířová
  - A weekly commentary of Ferdinand Peroutka, in Czech, March 17 (Reel 9)
    On the decline of the economy in socialist Czechoslovakia
  - A weekly commentary of Ferdinand Peroutka, in Czech, April 16 (Reel 10)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003654
    On the youth in socialist Czechoslovakia
  - A weekly commentary of Ferdinand Peroutka, in Czech, October 27 (Reel 11)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003655
    On the anniversary of Czechoslovakia's foundation, Stalinism, and political culture in Poland
  - An interview with Peroutka by Kárnet (?), Part 1, in Czech, 1967 (Reel 12)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003658 (part)
    On Czech literature and culture
  - An interview with Peroutka by Kárnet (?), Part 2, in Czech, 1967 (Reel 13)
    On Czech literature and culture, unfinished
  - Fragment of an interview with Peroutka by Kárnet (?), in Czech, undated (Reel 14)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003661
    On communism
  - Dialogue between Peroutka and Karel Steinbach, with reminiscences of their New Year's Eve celebrations in Czechoslovakia, Part 1, unedited, in Czech, circa 1971 (Reel 15)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003662 (part)
  - Dialogue between Peroutka and Karel Steinbach, with reminiscences of their New Year's Eve celebrations in Czechoslovakia, Part 2, unedited, in Czech, circa 1971 (Reel 16)
  - Lecture by Jaroslav Stránský about a poet František Gellner with readings from Gellner's writings, Part 1, in Czech, circa 1964 (Reel 17)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003663 (part)
  - Lecture by Jaroslav Stránský about a poet František Gellner with readings from Gellner's writings, Part 2, in Czech, circa 1964 (Reel 18)
  - Interview with Peroutka by Z. Eliáš (?), Part 1, unedited, in Czech, undated (Reel 19)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003664 (part)
    On Czechoslovak political culture
  - Interview with Peroutka by Z. Eliáš (?), Part 1, unedited, in Czech, undated (Reel 20)
  - Interview with Peroutka by Z. Eliáš (?), Part 1, edited, in Czech, undated (Reel 21)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003665 (part)
  - Interview with Peroutka by Z. Eliáš (?), Part 2, edited, in Czech, undated (Reel 22)
  - Interview with Peroutka by Z. Eliáš (?), Part 3, edited, in Czech, undated (Reel 23)
  - Radio Free Europe New Year's Eve program moderated by Jirka Planér, Part 1, in Czech, circa 1971 (Reel 24)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003671 (part)
  - Radio Free Europe New Year's Eve program moderated by Jirka Planér, Part 2, in Czech, circa 1971 (Reel 25)
    Contains the edited version of a dialogue between Peroutka and Karel Steinbach, with reminiscences of their New Year's Eve celebrations in Czechoslovakia
  - Fragment of an interview with Peroutka, in Czech, undated (Reel 26)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003672
    On Czechoslovak and European history and politics, and on Jan Masaryk and his passing
  - Fragment of an interview with Peroutka, in Czech, undated (Reel 27)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003673
  - Fragment of an interview with Peroutka, in Czech, undated (Reel 28)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003675
    On Czechoslovak and European history and politics, Czechoslovak communists and Julius Fučík
  - Fragment of an interview with Peroutka, in Czech, undated (Reel 29)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003677
  - Fragment of an interview with Peroutka, in Czech, undated (Reel 30)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003678
    On Czechoslovak communists and Klement Gottwald
  - Fragment of an interview with Peroutka, in Czech, undated (Reel 31)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003679
  - Fragment of an interview with Peroutka, in Czech, undated (Reel 32)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003681
    On Stalin's purges in Czechoslovakia
  - Fragment of an interview with Peroutka, in Czech, undated (Reel 33)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003682
    On Stalin's purges and communism in Czechoslovakia
  - Fragment of an interview with Peroutka, in Czech, undated (Reel 34)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003683
  - Fragment of an interview with Peroutka, in Czech, undated (Reel 35)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003684
    On the events surrounding the 1948 communist putsch
  - Fragment of an interview with Peroutka, in Czech, undated (Reel 36)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003685
    On the events leading to Peroutka's emigration from Czechoslovakia in 1948 and on Vladimír Clementis
  - Fragment of an interview with Peroutka, in Czech, undated (Reel 37)
    Use copy reference number: 84052_a_0003688